<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Articles concerning the surrender of VVorcester</title>
            <title>Articles concerning the surrender of Worcester.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 4 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A25918</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3816</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R216538</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99828265</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99828265</idno>
            <idno type="VID">32692</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A25918)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 32692)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1963:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Articles concerning the surrender of VVorcester</title>
                  <title>Articles concerning the surrender of Worcester.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 5, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Leonard Lichfield, printer to the Vniversity,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>A.D.1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Lincoln College Library, Oxford.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Worcester (England) --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:32692:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:32692:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ARTICLES CONCERNING THE SVRRENDER OF WORCESTER.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>OXFORD, Printed by <hi>Leonard Lichfield,</hi> Printer to the Vniverſity, <hi>A. D.</hi> 1646.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="articles_of_peace_treaty">
            <pb facs="tcp:32692:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:32692:2"/>
            <head>Articles of Agreement for the Surrender of the Citty and Garriſon of WORCESTER, and the Forts belonging there unto, concluded <hi>July</hi> the 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 1646. Between Col. <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Rainborow</hi> on the behalfe of his Excellency Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax</hi> Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall of the Forces raiſed by the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and Col. <hi>Hen. Waſhington</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor of <hi>Worceſter.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat the city of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> with all <hi>Forts, Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, Stores and Proviſion of Warre there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto belonging,</hi> ſhall be delivered without willfull ſpoile and imbezle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, unto his Excellencie <hi>Sir Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:32692:3"/>Fairefax,</hi> or to ſuch as he ſhall appoint to receive them, upon the <hi>23.</hi> of this inſtant <hi>Iuly,</hi> at <hi>tenne of the</hi> Clocke in the mornin, in ſuch man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and with ſuch exceptions as are contained in the Enſuing Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> That on the <hi>Twenty third</hi> day of <hi>Iuly,</hi> The Governour, and all Officers and Souldiers of the Garriſon, with all other Perſons therein that will, ſhall march out of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> with their Horſes, Armes and Baggage properly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to them, to any place within one Mile of <hi>Worceſter</hi> which the <hi>Governour</hi> ſhall chuſe, where all their <hi>Horſes</hi> and <hi>Armes,</hi> except what are allowed in the enſuing Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, ſhall be delivered up to ſuch
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:32692:3"/>as his Excellencie <hi>Sir Thomas Fairefax</hi> ſhall appoynt, all the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers ſhall be disbanded, and all ſuch both <hi>Officers, Souldiers,</hi> and others as ſhall ingage themſelves by promiſe never to beare Armes any more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> nor do any thing willfully to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice of their Affaires, ſhall have the benefit of theſe Enſuing Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3</hi> That all ſuch as ſhall deſire to goe to their own homes, or private friends, ſhall have the Generalls Paſſe and Protection for their peaceable repaires and abode at their ſeverall places they ſhall deſire to goe unto, the Governor to paſſe with all Horſes, Armes, and Bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage properly belonging to him, each
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:32692:4"/>Colonell to paſſe with three Horſes, each Lieut. Colonell, and Serg. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor with two Horſes, each Captain Lieutenant and Coronet with one Horſe, and every perſon not under the degree of an Eſquire with three Horſes, and all of them with their Armes and Goods properly belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to them to be carried on their Horſes, and all Souldiers with their Swords, and ſuch Baggage as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly belong to them, which they carry about them.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4</hi> That all Perſons which are to have the benefit of the preceding Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, ſhall if they deſire it, have Paſſes to goe beyond Seas: provided they depart this Kingdome within two Months after the ſurrender of the Towne.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:32692:4"/> 
               <hi>5</hi> That the Citty and Garriſon of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> and all the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants thereof, ſhall be preſerved from all Plunder and violence of the Souldiers.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <hi>6</hi> That Sir <hi>William Ruſſell</hi> now reſiding in <hi>Worceſter</hi> be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted from any benefit of theſe Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
